usatf.org 2006-06-15

# USATF - Privacy Statement

| 

USA Track & Field Privacy Statement

Revised 10-9-01

Sections

  1. The organization collecting the information.
  2. What personally identifiable information is collected from you through our website and how it's used.
  3. With whom the information may be shared and other kinds of disclosures.
  4. The kind of security procedures that are in place to protect the loss, misuse, or alteration of information under USATF's control.
  5. What choices are available to you regarding collection, use, and distribution of the information and how you can correct any inaccuracies in the information.

If you feel that we are not abiding by our posted privacy statement, you should first contact Keith Lively, Multimedia Communications Coordinator, at [Keith.Lively@usatf.org](mailto:Keith.Lively@usatf.org) or at (317) 713-4672. If you do not receive acknowledgment of your inquiry or your inquiry has not been satisfactorily addressed, you should then contact Jill Pilgrim, General Counsel/Director of Business Affairs, at [Jill.Pilgrim@usatf.org](mailto:Jill.Pilgrim@usatf.org) or at (317) 713-4683.

1\. The Organization Collecting the Information

USA Track & Field (USATF) is the sole owner of the information collected on its sites and through other means. We will not sell, share, rent, or otherwise disclose this information to other parties other than as disclosed in this statement.

This website contains links to other sites. Please be aware that USATF is not responsible for the privacy practices of other sites. We encourage our users to take appropriate precautions when leaving our site and to read the privacy statements of each and every web site that collects personally identifiable information. This privacy statement applies solely to information collected by this website.

2\. What personally identifiable information is collected from you through our website and how it's used.

USATF collects information from our users at several different points throughout our website and from other sources. This section describes these points of collection.

Membership Registration

In order to become a member of USATF, an applicant must first complete a membership registration form. During registration an applicant is required to give contact information such as name, address, phone number, and e-mail address. This information is used to create a membership card and to contact the member about topics in which he/she has expressed an interest. All information is required unless otherwise stated on the membership form. This privacy policy governs both members who apply online or otherwise.

Event/Meet Registration

In order to register for an event through a USATF website, an entrant is required to give contact information such as name, address, phone number, and e-mail address, as well as information about his/her event(s)--which may include age, sex, qualifying mark(s), etc. USATF sends information about entrants (such as name, age, address, event entered, qualifying mark, etc.) to meet management personnel so they can properly and accurately prepare entry lists and conduct the event.

National Championships Registration

In order to register for the USA National Championships through the USATF website, an entrant must first be a member of USATF (see membership registration above). On the entry form, an entrant is required to provide his/her membership number and information about his/her qualifying mark(s). USATF sends information about entrants (such as name, age, sex, address, event entered, qualifying mark, etc.) to meet management personnel so they can properly and accurately prepare entry lists and conduct the event.

Newsletters

If a user subscribes to our newsletter(s), we ask for contact information such as name and e-mail address. These e-mail addresses and names are never shared outside our organization, except as described in this privacy statement.

Merchandise Order

We request information from customers on our merchandise order forms. A customer must provide contact information (such as name and shipping address) and financial information (such as credit card number and expiration date). This information is used to fill customers' orders and process payment. If we have trouble processing an order, this contact information is used to get in touch with the customer. Customers' names and addresses may be shared with third parties as necessary to process, fulfill, or ship orders. Financial information is never shared inside or outside our organization, except as necessary to process the order.

Contests and Surveys

From time to time, we may conduct contests or surveys. Participation in these contests or surveys is completely voluntary, and thus the user has a choice about whether or not to disclose the information requested. Information from these contests and surveys may be combined with other information we have about you, but is never shared except in the form of aggregate statistics.

Log Files

We use standard server log files to analyze trends, administer the site, and gather broad demographic information for aggregate use. This log file information is not linked to personally identifiable information, and all information gleaned from log files is used only in the aggregate.

Cookies

A cookie is a piece of data stored on the user's hard drive containing information about the user. When someone logs into the members-only area, for example, we set a per-session cookie that identifies this person as a legitimate member. This cookie allows us to keep track of who the user is while he/she is browsing the members-only pages so he/she won't have to log back in each time he/she visits a new page. Per-session cookies expire after the user leaves our website (i.e. once the users closes his/her web browser, the cookie is deleted from his/her system).

If a user rejects the cookie, he/she may still use most parts of our site. The only drawback is that the user will have limited access in some areas of our site.

Other Collection Points

We may also collect information from people through other means such as on the telephone, by e-mail, by fax, on paper, and in person. This privacy policy governs the use and disclosure of that information as well.

3\. With whom the information may be shared and other kinds of disclosures.

We occasionally share information with other USATF entities and third parties. This section describes what information we share and with whom.

Sharing with USATF entities

USATF Associations receive reports about members in their Association, including name, address, phone, e-mail address, etc. This information is used to contact members about general-interest matters and specialized topics in the same manner as described in Section 2 above. Associations may occasionally share aggregated demographic information with their partners and advertisers. Again, this is not linked to any personal information that can identify any individual person.

USATF Associations are required to abide by the National USATF privacy policy. Certain Associations may have their own privacy policies, but these will always be more restrictive, never less, than the national policy. The national policy always supersedes any Association's policies. Please direct any questions first to the Association and then to the National Office.

Sharing with non-USATF third parties

For elite athletes, we also share information from your profile and other sources with the United States Olympic Committee (USOC), the United States Anti-Doping Agency (USADA), the International Olympic Committee (IOC), and the International Amateur Athletic Federation (IAAF) for administrative purposes. This helps athletes avoid re-entering their information for each organization. These organizations' respective privacy policies govern the use of your information for their purposes.

USATF occasionally enters into partnerships with other organizations to provide valuable services to the running/track & field community. When USATF provides the services or collects information from such services, this privacy statement will govern the use of such information for the partnership.

When someone signs up for an event, we pass on the necessary information (name, address, age) to the race or meet management personnel. These parties are not allowed to use personally identifiable information except for the purpose of entering the person in the event. However, this information may be used to create programs, heat sheets, and results for the meet which may include the entrants' name, home city and state, age, etc. USATF has advised meet management personnel that if they plan to use this information for purposes other than entering a person in the event, they must notify USATF. USATF will in turn notify entrants, and entrants will have the option of being excluded from such other purposes at the time of registration.

We use an outside shipping company to ship orders, an outside printing company to print certain publications, and a credit card processing company to bill users for goods and services. These companies are directed not to retain, share, store, or use personally identifiable information for any secondary purpose.

We occasionally share aggregated demographic information with our corporate sponsors, suppliers, partners, and advertisers. This is not linked to any personal information that can identify any individual person.

We occasionally provide postal mailing lists to magazines which we think might be of interest to our members. From time to time, we also provide postal or e-mail lists to USATF corporate sponsors, suppliers, or other partners for the specific purpose of offering discounts or perquisites which we think might be of interest to our members. These companies or organizations are directed not to use these mailing lists for any other purposes or to disclose them to any third party. Members may opt out of inclusion in such lists on our website or by writing to the USATF National Office.

We will also share information to prevent fraud, to respond to a legal process, or as otherwise required by law.

Other kinds of disclosures of personal information

USATF Officers, employees, Association Officers, as well as USATF Committee members, Sub-Committee members, USOC and IAAF Representatives, and USATF Board members, may have their name, address, fax number, phone number, and e-mail (work and/or home for each) listed both on the website and in print for contact purposes. Any person who accepts an official position with USATF agrees to have his/her contact information made available to USATF's members and the public, unless requested otherwise.

Elite athletes and Hall of Famers may have their biographies posted on the USATF website or otherwise published by USATF. These people agree to have certain information about themselves communicated to the public, including, but not limited to, name, home city and state, age, educational background, etc. The names of elite athletes who are subject to drug testing may also be posted on our website and reported to the media.

Children

In cases where USATF collects personally identifiable information from children under the age of 18, we require parental consent before the collection is completed. For example, the USATF membership application requires a parent's or guardian's "signature" before it will be accepted. The signature on the application evidences the parent's or guardian's consent to have the child's information used in accordance with this privacy policy. Upon request, a parent or guardian may obtain the information that his or her child has provided to USATF.

4\. The kind of security procedures that are in place to protect the loss, misuse, or alteration of information under USATF's control.

This website takes every reasonable precaution to protect users' information. When users submit sensitive information via the website, the information is protected both on- and off-line.

When our registration forms ask users to enter sensitive information (such as credit card number and/or social security number), that information is encrypted and is protected with industry-standard encryption software (SSL). While on a secure page, such as our membership application, the lock icon at the bottom of web browsers (i.e. Netscape Navigator, Microsoft Internet Explorer) appears locked. If not locked, any information a user submits is not secure, and USATF will not be responsible for the loss or theft of such information.

While we use SSL encryption to protect sensitive information online, we also make every reasonable effort to protect users' information off-line. Access to users' information, not only the sensitive information mentioned above, is restricted in our organization. Only those employees who need the information to perform their job are granted access to personally identifiable information. All employees are kept up-to-date on our security and privacy practices and are reminded about the importance we place on privacy.

USATF makes every reasonable effort to safeguard sensitive information by regularly reviewing our security standards and practices to protect against unauthorized access. If you have any questions about the security at our website, you can send an e-mail to [Keith.Lively@usatf.org](mailto:Keith.Lively@usatf.org).

5\. What choices are available to you regarding collection, use, and distribution of the information and how you can correct any inaccuracies in the information.

Choice and opting in/out

We send all new members a welcoming e-mail to confirm their membership status. Once the registration is complete, members may update their membership profile to indicate what types of mailing they wish to receive (several mailing categories are set by default). Established members will receive only communications that fall into the categories in which they have expressed interest. However, members will occasionally receive important communications from us regardless of their mailing preferences (for example to confirm a membership renewal, to confirm an event entry, or to request required membership information that is missing).

Non-members may opt in or out of various mailings by following the instructions provided at the bottom of e-mail messages or as described on our website.

Users of our site are always notified when their information is being collected by any outside parties. We do this so our users can make an informed choice as to whether they should proceed with services that require an outside party.

Correction/Updating Personal Information

If a user's personally identifiable information changes (such as your address, phone, e-mail address, etc.), we will endeavor to provide a way to correct or update that personal data provided to us. This can usually be done at the member profile page (accessed through the members-only area) or by contacting your local Association or the National Office.

For elite athletes, biographies are updated throughout the year, and any inaccuracies may be corrected by notifying Jill Geer, Director of Communications, at [Jill.Geer@usatf.org](mailto:Jill.Geer@usatf.org). Such changes will be reflected in the next release of the athlete biographies.

For the website and printed directories, contact information may be corrected/added/removed by contacting Sherry Quack, Association and Member Services Coordinator, at [Sherry.Quack@usatf.org](mailto:Sherry.Quack@usatf.org) or at (317) 713-4685.

Notification of Changes

If USATF changes its privacy policy, we will post a notice of the change on our homepage for at least seven days so our users are always aware of what information we collect, how we use it, and under what circumstances, if any, we disclose it. If at any point USATF decides to use personally identifiable information in a manner different from that stated at the time it was collected, users will have a choice whether to consent to such use.

| 

* * *

* * *

* * *

* * *

* * *
